A Guide to the Hans Rademacher papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA128
Rockefeller Archive Center
Hans Rademacher papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
circa 1910-1967, 1983
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rademacher, Hans
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA128
14.55 Cubic Feet 16 document boxes
Biographical/Historical note
Hans Rademacher (1892-1969), a mathematician, was a visiting professor (1964-1965) and affiliate (1966-1969) at the Rockefeller University. This German-born authority in number theory received his Ph.D. from the University of Göttingen (Germany) in 1917. The bulk of Rademacher's academic career in the U.S. was spent at the University of Pennsylvania where, upon his retirement in 1962, he was awarded the title of Professor Emeritus.
Rademacher's early work, 1910-1934, focused on the measurability of real variables, differentiability and integration. He developed systems of orthogonal functions known as the "Rademacher Functions". In 1923, Rademacher examined the theory of functions of complex variables, at which time he perfected the "sieve method" and applied it to algebraic numbers. Following his arrival to the U.S. in 1934, Rademacher studied as a visiting Rockefeller Fellow at the University of Pennsylvania. From the mid 1930's to the 1960's., he worked on Fourier coefficients of modular forms, formulated the partition number and coefficients of the modular invariant, and developed his renowned analytic number theory.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order by series.
Related Materials
14 Additional record storage cartons of Rademacher materials have been received by RAC post 1996. (Boxes 1-12, including two Box 8's and Box 10A). All additional Rademacher materials are closed to scholarly research pending further processing.
See AC.2008.062 Hans Rademacher papers, Rockefeller University Faculty.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 R117
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: notes, correspondence, manuscripts, reprints, printed materials, galleys, and photographs.
Number theory; Calculus; Geometry; Mathematics; Algebra
- College Notes, 1910-1916; 1; 0.8 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Notes from classes attended at Göttingen University in Germany. Professors include Hilbert, Katz, Klein, Landau and Wegl. The material includes algebra, analytical geometry, integral calculus, mechanics and theory of functions.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Logic, Prof. E. Müller, Göttingen, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Einführung in die Differential und Integral Rechnung I. Prof. Klein, Summer Semester, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Analytische Geometrie, Dr. Wegl, Summer Semester, [Analytical Geometry], 1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Determinanten, Prof. Wegl, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Einführung in die Differential und Integral Rechnung, Prof. Klein, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gewöhnliche Differential Gleichungen, Prof. Hilbert, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kurven und Flächen, Prof Wegl, [Curves and Surface Area], 1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Courant Algebra, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Psychologie der Malerei, Prof. Katz, [Psychology of Art], 1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Über Sogenannte Mathematische Unterhaltungen und Spiele, [About so-called Mathematics Maintenance and play], 1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Funktionen Theorie, Göttingen, [Theory of Functions], 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Funktionalgleichung und der Funktion, [Functional Equations and their functions], 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mechanik, Prof. Hilbert, [Mechanics], 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cartheodory Conforme Abbildungen I, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ausgewählte Kapitel der Statistischen Mechanik, Prof. Hilbert, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - January, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Eineindeutige Abbildungen und Messbarkeit, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Course Notes, 1918-1963; 2; 3.3 Cubic Feet
  Teaching notes from Rademacher's years at the University of Berlin, Swarthmore College and the University of Pennsylvania. Notes include algebra, analytical geometry, calculus, differential equations, elementary additive number theory, modular functions and number theory.
  - Übungen zur Algebra, Sept., [Exercises for Algebra], 1918 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Schur-Hohere Zahlen Theorie, [Schur-Hohere Number Theory], 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mathematische Methoden und Probleme, [Mathematical Methods and Problems], 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Waring's Problem (Neuere Analytische Methoden der Additen Zahl Theorie), [New Analytical Methods of the Addition Number Theory], 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notes, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Elliptische Funktionen, [Elliptical Functions], 1927 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notes, 1928 May 18 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gruppentheorie, Breslau, [Group Theory], 1928 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Differential Rechnung, Breslau, [Differential Calculations], 1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Analytical Number Theory, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Integralrechnung II, [Integral Calculations], 1929 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Funktionen Theorie, Breslau [Theory of Functions], 1930 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Aufgaben Dec, [Assignments], 1931 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Theorie der Algebrandern Zahlentheorie, Breslau,[Theory of Algebraic Number Theory], 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Analytische Geometrie I, [Analytical Geometry I], 1933 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Analytische Geometrie I, [Analytical Geometry I], 1933 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Analytische Geometrie I, [Analytical Geometry I], 1933 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Elementary Additive Number Theory, 1935-1936; folder 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Elementary Additive Number Theory, 1935-1936; folder 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Selected Topics in Higher Algebra, 1936; folder 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Selected Topics in Higher Algebra, 1936; folder 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - On the Accumulation of Errors in Processes of Integration on High Speed Calculating Machines, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Analytic Number Theory, Philadelphia, 1937-1938; folder 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Analytic Number Theory, Philadelphia, 1937-1938; folder 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Analytic Additive Number Theory I, University of Pennsylvania, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Modular Functions, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Calculus of Variations, University of Pennsylvania, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Calculus of Variations, University of Pennsylvania, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Algebraic Theory of Numbers, Spring Term, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Modern Theory of Functions, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Analytic Additive Number Theory Chaps. 14 and 15, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Mordell, Geometry of Numbers, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - A Survey of Higher Mathematics, NYU, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Analytic Prime Number Theory, Spring Term, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dedekind Sums, Princeton, 1953 May (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Elliptic Functions, Fall Term, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Theory of Partitions, 1954 December 24 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Theory of Functions of Real Variables, Philadelphia, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Würges, Gerhard "Theory of Algebraic Numbers", notes from lectures held at the Mathematisches Institut, Göttingen, Germany in winter semester, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Notes to Analytic Number Theory, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Functions of Several Complex Variables (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Table of Periodic Continued Fractions released from the Research Computation Section at Lockhead, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Geometry, New York University, Fall Term, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Analytic Number Theory, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - On Prime Numbers, Pennsylvania State University, 1963 May 24 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Notes from, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Primitive Root Modules (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Notes (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Eine Bemerkung über die Heckeschen Operation T (n) [An observation about the Heckeschen Operation T(n)] (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Notes (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Notes (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Algebraic Numbers (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Experimental Function Logarithm (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Dedekind Sums and Binary Quadratic Forms (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Prime numbers and the zeroes of the........ (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Modular Functions (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Complex Multiplication (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oberfläche des Hegelstumpfes (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Abschritt II. Mechanik der Systeme von Masserysunkten (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Klein, Differential und Integralrechnung I (Forsetzung) [Diminutive, Differential and Integral Calculations I (?)] (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Toeplitz Funktion Theorie (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Japanese-notebook (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Part IV. The Circle Method. Chapter XIV. Analytic Theory of Partitions (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Zur Analysis Situs (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Introduction to the Theory of Functions of Complex Variables (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Periodic Functions of n Variables and zn Variables (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Special Relativity Theory (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - On the Phragmen-Lindelöf Theorem and some applications (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Gamma Function and Mellin's Theory of Reciprocal Functions (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Analytic Number Theory (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Schwartz's Theory of Distributions (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Introduction to Hecke's Theory of Modular Forms (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Theory of Numbers (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Theory of Differential Equations (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Notes (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Schloss Bischofstein bei Leugenfeld (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Virevgradoffs Method (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - The Transcendence of e and (Pi) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Number Theory (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Dürer's Magic Square (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Number Theory (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Notes (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Number Theory in Certain Algebraic Fields (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Notes (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1936-1966; 3; 0.1 Cubic Feet
  Included are correspondences with Joseph Diamond, Theodor Eastmann, Dr. Heisig and Morris Newman various correspondences between the years 1964 and 1965.
  - Correspondence regarding der Neubearbeitung von Band I, 1936-1937 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    "Algebra und Zahlentheorie der Enzyklopädie der Mathematischen Wissenschaften", 1936-1937 [Algebra and the Number theory of the Encyclopedia of Mathematical Scholars].
  - Correspondence between Theodor Estermann and Hans Rademacher, 1937 July (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence between Dr. Heisig and Hans Rademacher, 1939 September (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondences, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Letter from Morris Newman, Chief Numerical Analysis, Section IBS to Hans Rademacher, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - A Correspondence from H. Rademacher to Mr. Joseph Diamond on the Calculations for the shape of an axis symmetric oval (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Manuscripts, 1929-1966; 4; 1 Cubic Feet
  Included are manuscripts dealing with analytical number theory, the human brain in dream and waking states, integral truths, mathematical theories by other leading mathematicians, modular invariants and partition functions.
  - Theorie der algebraischen Fahlkoiper (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Die Zyklische Gruppe vom Grade A1...... Am [The cycle of Groups from Grade A1 and Am] (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Elements of T in the first four residue sequences of 7 (A mathematical table) (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Analytic Additive Number Theory (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Sylvester's formula (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - On Modular Functions (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Schur's method (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - On a theorem of Besicovitch (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Report of the Ad Hoc Committee on Faculty Structure, 1962 November 16 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - An essay on the human brain in dream and waking states (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Integral Truth II, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Rademacher-Zuckerman, University of Pennsylvania, Graduate School, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - On the Accumulation of Errors in Processes of Integration, University of Pennsylvania, 1950 June (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Plotkin's case, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Enjoyment of Mathematics, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Collected papers of G. H. Hardy, volume 1, notes, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - A convergent series for the partition function p(n) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - On the Partition Function p(n) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - On the Partition Function p(n) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - On the expansion of the Partition Function p(n) in a series (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Theory of Partitions (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - On the Partition Function (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Über das Verhältnis der Analysis zur Zahlentheorie" [About the relation of Analysis to the Number theory] (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - "Helly's Theorems on Convex Domains and Tchebycheff's Approximation Problem" by Hans Rademacher & I.J. Schoenberg (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - "The Fourier coefficients of the modular invariant" (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Part IV. The Circle Method and Chapter XIV. Analytic Theory of Partitions (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "Die Reziprozitaetsformel fuer Dedekindsche Summen" by Hans Rademacher [The Reciprocal Formula for Dedekind's Sums] (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - "On the Precision of a Certain Procedure of Numerical Integration" Preliminary Report by Hans Rademacher (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript-notes (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Theorie der Reillers Funktion und der Lebesuesdium Tutegrele (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Nearly discovered unsolved problems (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Über Totale und Partielle Differengierbarkeit von Funktionen mehrerer Variabeln und über die Funktional Determinanten [About Total and Partial Differentiality for Functions of various variables and of the functional determinants] (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Die Bairerchen Klassur und die Analytische Darstellbarkeit reeller Funktionen (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Mathematics in the 19th century (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Factorization and Farey Fractions (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "Phragmen-Lindelof Theorem and Subharmonic Functions" by Hans Rademacher (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - On Differential Quotients (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "An Iteration Method for Computation with Laurent Series" written by H.A. Rademacher with I.J. Schoenberg (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Reprints, 1919-1969; 5; 0.1 Cubic Feet
  Reprints are grouped in blocks of years.
  - Reprints, 1919-1931 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Reprints, 1932-1948 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Kuhlenbeck, Hartwig "Schopenhauers Bedeutung für die Neurologie" in Der Nervenarzt, vol. 4, pp. 177-182, 1961 April (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Reprints, 1950-1969, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - The Phragmen-Lindelöf Theorem and some Applications (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Journals and Brochures, undated; 6; 0.1 Cubic Feet
  Includes the Phragmen-Lindelöf theorem and some of its applications, an issue of The Bulletin and a monument to Hans Rademacher.
  - The Bulletin, vol. 14. No. 33. Bonn, 1966 September 6 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Monument to a Mathematician-The Hans Rademacher Instructorships-at the University of Pennsylvania (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Galleys, undated; 7; 0.1 Cubic Feet
  Includes the Greensche formula for linear differential gleichnungen zweiter ordnung and the partition function.
  - Greensche Formula für Linear Differentialgleichnungen Zweiter Ordnung [Greensche Formula for Linear Differential] (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - On the Partition Function p(n) (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Lectures, Presentations and Reports, 8; 0.9 Cubic Feet
  Includes lectures given at the meeting of the American Mathematical Society, Haverford College, Johns Hopkins, the University of Oregon, University of Pennsylvania and Tate Institute. Topics include additive number theory, analytical number theory, elementary mathematics, higher math and numerical analysis.
  - Lecture, Johns Hopkins University, 1937 May 20 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - "Abstract of a paper to be presented before the meeting of the American Mathematical Society, New York City, 1938 September 6-9 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - "The Linkage of Genes", lecture before the Zoological Seminar, 1943 January 7 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Lectures on the Analytic Number Theory, NYU., 1949 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - The Renaissance-A Symposium, 1952 February 8-10 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Lectures given by Hans Rademacher while a visitor at Haverford College, fall semester, 1952-1953 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Lecture notes on Elementary Mathematics from an advanced viewpoint from lectures given at the summer conference in collegiate mathematics at the University of Oregon, 1954 June 23-August 11 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Lecture notes on Analytic Additive Number Theory from lectures given at the summer conference in collegiate mathematics at the University of Oregon, 1954 June 21-August 13 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Lectures at Tate Institute, 1954-1955 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "The Universe of Mathematics" orientation lecture before the freshman class, 1958 October (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Lecture to the Academic Year Institute, 1960 December 14 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Lecture before the Research Club of the University of Pennsylvania, 1962 November 14 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Elementary Mathematics from a Higher Point of View, 1980 July 14 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Lecture 2. A New Approach to Numerical Analysis, II (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Lecture 3. On Euclidean sets having only two distances between points (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Lecture 4. The Kakeya Problem (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Additive Number Theory and Modular Functions (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Disposition der Neuauflage des Bandes Algebra und Zahlentheorie der Encyklopädie der Mathematischen Wissenschaften (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - The Senate Committee on Faculty Procedures: Interim Report (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Lecture IV. The Explicit Formula for the Partition Function (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Rademacher Photos and Illustrations, undated; 9; 2 folders
  An unlabeled group photo and illustrations of nudes.
  Photographs
  - Group Photo (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Nude Illustrations (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Accesson 2008.062 - Correspondence, 1928-1967; 10
  Arrangement
  Series 10 is arranged chronologically by year. Within each year, the material is further arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent (personal or institutional name).
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence includes documentation of memberships, activities, lecture and speaking engagements, personal and professional correspondence, general files and select bills and receipts.
  The first file within each year often contains some miscellaneous files or correspondence, and followed by the beginning of the alphabetical correspondence.
  - Correspondence - A - Z, 1928-1936 (Box 17, Folder 1-14)
  - Correspondence - A - Z, 1937-1944 (Box 18, Folder 1-16)
  - Correspondence - A - Z, 1945-1951 (Box 19, Folder 1-15)
  - Correspondence - A - Z, 1952-1957 (Box 20, Folder 1-16)
  - Correspondence - A - Z, 1958-1962 (Box 21, Folder 1-16)
  - Correspondence - A - Z, 1963-1967 (Box 22, Folder 1-13)
  - Notebook (Box 22, Folder 14)